The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PETER KEMPTHORNE: Today's
topic is portfolio theory.
An it's really one of the most
important topics in finance.
We're going to go through the
historical theory of portfolio
optimization, beginning
with Markowitz Mean-Variance
Optimization, where we
look at portfolios in terms
of their performance
characteristics
as determined by the mean return
and the volatility returns.
This analysis gets extended
by looking at also investing
with a risk-free asset.
The initial theory
on portfolio analysis
didn't consider
investing in cash,
but just investing
in risky assets.
The problem changes
quite dramatically when
we add the risk-free asset.
Then the topic of utility
theory, von Neumann-Morgenstern
utility theory, in
statistical decision theory,
we are trying to make
decisions under uncertainty
in a rational way.
And von Neumann and Morgenstern
developed a expected utility
hypothesis for rational
decision making.
And that's really very
important motivator
for decision analysis generally
and portfolio selection
in particular.
So we'll go through that.
Then we'll turn to portfolio
optimization constraints.
There are realistic issues
when you have-- well,
there's how much money
you have to invest,
how much capital you have
to invest, whether you could
short securities or not,
whether there are sort
of limits in capacity
of different assets
you might want to trade.
Those can come into play
and affect the solutions.
All of these methods
are driven by estimates
of how well we
expect assets to do,
so estimating returns
or estimating alphas,
and also estimating the
volatilities and correlations
amongst the assets
were trading in.
Most of the theory we'll
talk about today deals
with estimates-- well,
with the problem where
we're assuming basically
certainty in terms
of understanding those
underlying return
characteristics, the means,
variances, correlations.
But when we have to estimate
those that raises problems.
And finally, we'll
finish up talking
about some alternative
risk measures, which
extend the
straightforward mean--
or simple
mean-variance analysis.
Now the mean-variance analysis
is a single-period analysis.
What we want to do is
consider investing our capital
in some assets.
And we want to do so
for just a single period
and do so optimally.
So in terms of notation,
we'll consider risky assets
indexed by i, 1 through m.
Single-period returns will
be a multivariate vector
of those returns.
The mean and covariance
of these assets
are represented in vector of
returns and covariance matrix
of squared volatilities,
the variances
of the assets along
the diagonals,
and the covariances
on the off-diagonals.
A portfolio will be represented
as basically a weighting
of our investment
in these m assets.
So we'll have a vector w,
consisting of w_1 up to w_m.
I'm giving the relative
weights and absolute weights
of those investments.
We'll assume that we have one
unit of capital to invest.
So the sum of these
weights equals 1.
And the portfolio return
has expected return
given by the expectation
of this linear combination
of the returns, which is simply
the same linear combination
of the underlying expectations.
And the variance
of the portfolio
is given by the variance
of the weighted average
of the individual
returns, which is
given by this quadratic form
in the covariance matrix.
So we've gone through this--
or you understand, I think,
these calculations from our
discussion in time series.
And that's quite simple.
Now before going into
the theory for this,
let's look at the problem.
Let's look at the
portfolio analysis problem
in a very simplified setting.
So we're just going
to consider two assets
and talk about optimal
portfolios investing
in these two assets.
So m equals 2.
The first asset has
return R_1 with mean 0.15.
Now I'm going to think of
this as annualized return, so
a 15% annualized return
and a volatility of 25%.
The second asset has
expected return of 20%
and a volatility
of 30%, sigma_2.
These assets are
possibly correlated.
We'll let rho denote the
correlation between the two.
And a portfolio-- basically
all the portfolios
we could invest in, so
long as we are limited
to a unit of capital
and no shorting,
are given by portfolios
indexed by w,
basically the amount of money
we invest in the second asset.
So R_w is w R_2
plus 1 minus w R_1.
That's the return
on the portfolio
that invest in those
proportions in the two assets.
The expected return is
this linear combination,
which is given in matrix
form in the previous page--
or in the lecture notes.
And the variance, our
squared volatility is what?
It's 1 minus omega
squared times the variance
of R_1 plus w squared
times the variance of R_2.
Then we have a covariance
term that comes into play.
Now the mean-variance analysis
that Markowitz addressed
basically looks at the
feasible portfolio set.
We simplify things
by saying let's focus
just on the volatility or
variance and the expected
return of our portfolio.
So we can define the
feasible portfolio
set as the collection
of volatility return
pairs for all the assets--
or for all the portfolios.
And well, what is pi
star, that collection?
Basically what's the universe
of possible portfolios
we could construct?
In this two dimensional case
it's going to very simple.
In multidimensional cases
it's more complicated.
But what portfolios are optimal?
Sub-optimal?
How do we choose or identify
a particular portfolio
to invest in?
How's that choice made?
And is there any special
structure to these portfolios?
What you'll see in
the lecture today
is that the Markowitz theory
and extensions of that
provide really elegant
answers to these questions.
But let's understand
basically what's going on just
with this two-asset case.
And what I'm going to do
here is just simulate 500
weekly returns with different
values of the correlation
between the two assets.
And we want to examine
the cumulative returns
of each asset.
The asset returns in terms
of their means, volatilities,
and correlations,
a plot of pi star,
and the cumulative
returns of each asset
with a minimum
variance portfolio.
So let me just highlight
here that what we want here
is to be plotting sigma_omega
verses alpha_omega.
And we have two assets.
We have basically sigma_1
and alpha_1 corresponds
to our first asset.
Sigma_2 and alpha_2 corresponds
to our second asset.
So this point here
corresponds to w equals 0.
And the other corresponds to
w equals 1, so R_1 and R_2.
Now, what's going
to happen when we
combine assets in a portfolio?
Well, let's take a
look at the simulation.
OK, here is a graph
of the simulated asset
returns with basically a mean
returns given by 15%, 25%,
volatility is 20 to 30, and
with an asset correlation of 0.
So here's just a scatter
plot of the weekly returns.
There's basically no
apparent correlation there.
There actually is a
sample correlation,
because a sample from
these distributions
won't have perfectly
0 correlation.
On top, we have graphs of the
cumulative returns of the two
individual assets.
Rather obviously,
the higher graph
corresponds to the asset
with higher return, which
is asset 2.
And the green
corresponds to asset 1.
The graph on the
right, top right,
is the graph of the
feasible set as we allocate
between asset 1 and asset 2.
And so by the
simulation, this curve
corresponds to the
feasible set of portfolios.
And what's really remarkable
is that we can get basically
a reduction in the
volatility of the portfolio
without compromising,
and in fact improving,
the return the portfolio.
So if we invest fully in
asset 1, we're at this point.
As we increase-- as we start
allocating towards asset 2,
not only does the return of
asset of the portfolio go up,
but volatility goes down.
And let's see, in this
simulation, what I've done
is also plotted the return of
the portfolio corresponding
to the minimum variance.
So let's just look
the minimum variance
portfolio for a minute.
We have sigma squared
w is equal to 1
minus w squared plus w
squared sigma_2 squared--
this is sigma 1 squared.
And then plus 0 in
the case there's
no correlation between
the two assets.
If we want to minimize
this portfolio volatility,
we can take the derivative of
that with respect to the weight
and set that equal to 0.
So what's that equal to?
Well, it's-- let's see,
did I do this right?
Actually just with the
previous notes-- sorry,
R_1 is equal to 0.
OK, so we have 2, 1 minus w
sigma_1 squared times minus 1,
plus 2 w sigma_2
squared is equal to 0.
And so solving this, we get
w is equal to-- well, let's
see, you get 1 over
sigma_1 squared-- sorry,
1 over sigma_2 squared
divided by 1 over sigma_1
squared plus 1 over
sigma_2 squared.
If you solve this
out, you basically
get a weighting on the different
assets, which weights them
inversely proportional to
their squared volatility.
And with this
graph here, you can
see that the blue graph is a bit
closer to asset 1 than to asset
2's cumulative return.
That corresponds to giving to a
slightly higher weight to asset
1, because 1 over
sigma_1 squared
is bigger than 1
over sigma_2 squared.
Well, let's look at
what happens if we
consider negative correlations
between the two assets.
Well, actually, OK,
before we do that,
if you were going to choose
one of these portfolios
for investing, are
there any portfolios
that you wouldn't invest in?
And are any of these
portfolios sub-optimal
in terms of mean-variance?
AUDIENCE: w1.
PETER KEMPTHORNE: Well,
w1 is certainly infeasible
because we can increase
its mean and we
can decrease it's volatility.
So actually all of
these points here
are really sub-optimal
portfolios.
And from the minimum
variance portfolio,
which is basically getting
us the vertical tangent, all
the points from here up
to the asset 2, fully
investing in asset
2 are feasible.
And none of these portfolios
dominates the other.
Basically it's a trade-off
between return and volatility.
OK, so that's a really important
point that there really
are portfolios that you can
just disregard considering
that there are definite-- well,
when there's zero correlation,
there is a benefit to
diversifying across these two
assets.
So if you have an asset
and you are considering
pooling that asset with
another in your portfolio,
if those are fully
uncorrelated, then
you should be able to
improve your portfolio
by adding some allocation
to that second asset.
Let's look at the a more
negative correlation
between the two
assets of minus 0.4.
Here, you'll see that
there's basically
a tilt, negative tilt, to
the scatter plot of returns.
And with the portfolios
of two assets,
basically, the feasible
set, that feasible set
is actually stretching
further to the left.
So with a negative correlation
between the assets,
we're actually able to reduce
the volatility even more,
if that's what is
our preference.
If we go up here to minus 0.8,
it gets even more exaggerated.
Now what's going to
happen if we have
a correlation of negative
1 between these two assets?
AUDIENCE: The
portfolio can have 0?
PETER KEMPTHORNE: Yes, then
a portfolio of the two assets
can have zero variability.
So indeed with the
hedging strategies,
one often is considering
investing in assets consisting
of perhaps an underlying
security and some derivative
on that.
And that derivative,
if it's a future say,
could have basically a
negative 1 correlation.
So you could essentially
hedge out the volatility
almost perfectly.
So that special case actually
does exist quite frequently
and is exploited.
But it falls out just
from the simple analysis
of this simple simulation.
OK, let's also look at the going
to increase in the correlation.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: So if the volatility
of the whole portfolio
is zero, does that it mean
it will always be constant?
It will be--
PETER KEMPTHORNE:
Does that mean what?
AUDIENCE: So would
that mean since it
has zero variance it will
actually be constant over time?
The whole portfolio?
PETER KEMPTHORNE: OK, I mean,
if it has zero variance,
it should be constant.
Zero variance means that over--
that its value is a constant.
AUDIENCE: Is it a
good idea to do that?
PETER KEMPTHORNE: Well, in
terms of the markets nothing
has zero-- almost nothing
has zero volatility.
And so indeed-- but in the
pricing theory that Choongbum
will be discussing in
subsequent lectures,
if we have basically a portfolio
which has no volatility,
then its return should
be equal to whatever
a risk-free rate ought to be.
And so this particular
portfolio out
to be structured
so that it achieves
a return equal to a risk-free
rate, barring transaction costs
and frictions and all
that kind of thing.
But yeah.
OK, so if we increase the
correlation from 0 to 0.4,
well, we still get a benefit
of diversification but less.
We're basically not able to
lower the variance as much.
And it's even more exaggerated
with a correlation a 0.8.
Now, in looking
at the simulation,
one thing I want to
highlight to you now,
which will come
up later, is here
I've simulated returns according
to Gaussian distributions
with these means,
volatilities, and correlations.
And in the lower left panel,
I give the sample statistics.
Basically, the
maximum likelihood
estimate for all the parameters.
And what you'll see is that
these sample estimates differ
quite a bit from--
well, they differ
from the theoretical parameters.
In this case, the sample
volatility is almost exactly
on point for the first asset.
It's a bit below
0.287 for the second.
The sample mean is 0.21, which
is a bit high for the first.
And it's 0.321, which is also
a bit high for the second.
Let's just go back and look
at a couple of the others,
because it can get--
OK, well here's
one where the sample
means are 0.144 and 0.343.
And so those are actually quite
different from the population
parameters.
And at least, the second asset
has a much higher sample mean.
So it's important to note
that sample estimates can
have a certain amount
of variability.
It turns out that there's
less variability in estimating
covariances and correlations,
if the assumptions hold,
and greater variability
in the sample means.
So at the end of the
day we really need
to be very sensitive to
what estimates we use
and how much uncertainty
there is those.
OK, let's go back to
the lecture notes now.
View, screen, all right.
All right, so we've
just gone through how
we are evaluating different
portfolios in terms
of the pair of the-- basically
the mean of the portfolio
and the squared volatility
of the portfolio.
Higher expected returns
are obviously desirable.
Low volatility is desirable.
And so what Markowitz
did was to pose
this is a quadratic
programming problem, where
what we want to do is minimize
the squared volatility
of the portfolio subject
to a constraint on the mean
of the portfolio and considering
that we're fully invested.
So this mathematical problem is
a standard convex optimization
problem, a quadratic programming
problem, which is very simple.
And we solve it by
defining a Lagrangian.
Basically, we take our objective
function of the volatility.
And we want to minimize that.
We're going to use
a half factor just
to simplify the computations.
And then we add Lagrangians
for different constraints
of the problem.
So we have lambda_0 times
alpha_0 minus w prime alpha.
We want the mean
return, w prime alpha,
to be constrained to
equal alpha naught.
And we also want the sum
of the weights, w prime 1_m
to equal 1.
And the first-order
conditions of the Lagrangian
basically give us
those two constraints
for differentiating with respect
to lambda_1 and lambda_2.
The initial
first-order condition
with respect to the
portfolio weights
basically allows us to
solve for those weights.
Now, this first-order
condition is
going to solve our
problem, because if we
take the second-order
derivative of this Lagrangian,
it's going to be sigma.
So let me just point out if
we take d squared L by dw dw
prime, that's equal to our
covariance matrix sigma.
And that is a positive definite
or positive semi-definite
matrix.
So we indeed are
minimizing the problem.
So this is just a generalization
of basically a parabola
in multi-dimensions.
And we're trying
to minimize that.
Well, what's the
solution to this?
Well, first we can solve
for w, the weights,
in terms of lambda_1
and lambda_2.
So we take the first equation
of the first-order conditions
and basically pre-multiply
by sigma inverse across.
And we get w_0 is equal to
lambda_1 sigma inverse alpha
plus lambda_2 sigma
inverse the unit vector,
or vector of units.
And then we can just solve
for lambda_1 and lambda_2
by plugging this w_0 solution
into the second two equations.
And these two equations for the
second and third first-order
conditions is just a very
simple set of linear equations.
We basically have alpha_0 1
is equal to some matrix times
[lambda_1, lambda_2].
And that matrix,
a, b, c, is given
by alpha prime sigma inverse
alpha for the a element.
And the b and c elements are
those corresponding elements.
So this solves the problem.
And the variance of the optimal
portfolio with a given return
can also be solved
by just substituting
in these solutions.
So we get that for
a given alpha_0,
our target return,
the squared volatility
of that optimal portfolio
is this has that form.
Now, what's that form?
It's essentially a
parabola in alpha_0.
OK, so when we're looking
at-- is there an eraser?
here it is-- when we're
looking at this graph
here in the
two-dimensional case,
then there's
basically a parabola.
I can't draw
parabolas very well.
But there's a parabola
between those two points
that characterizes the thing.
And in multi-dimensional--
multiple assets,
it's just a multivariate
extension of that.
This particular problem can also
be looked at in two other ways.
Before we're looking at
minimizing the variance,
subject to a constraint
on the expected return.
We can also say,
well, let's maximize
the return, subject to a
constraint on the volatility.
And that problem basically
has the same Lagrangian.
And we can also consider just
maximizing a weighted average
of the return and have
a negative multiple
on the variance and consider
maximizing that expression.
This turns out to be the risk
aversion optimization, where
we basically are penalizing
portfolios w for how
much variance they have.
And the lambda factor
tells us how much penalty
to associate per variance unit.
And these are all
equivalent problems being
solved by the same Lagrangian.
And from these problems we can
define the efficient frontier,
which is the collection of
all possible solutions, where
we range the target
return amongst values that
are feasible and the
volatility amongst values
that are feasible as well.
So the efficient frontier
will just trace these.
And in our two-variable
case, our two-asset case--
we have sigma and alpha.
We have two assets.
It's basically a
parabola like that.
If we have another two assets
that we're investing with,
then if we consider the
two-asset portfolios of just
these two assets,
there's basically
another parabola there.
And as we consider different
other assets in the mix,
we basically get
all these parabolas
of two-asset portfolios.
And then combinations of
those two-asset portfolio
gives us our feasible set.
And so at the end of
the day, we basically
have a convex set of all
feasible assets, which
define the efficient frontier.
And the efficient
frontier is always
going to be basically the
top side of that curve.
Well, let's see, the
next topic considers
adding basically a risk-free
asset to invest in.
The problem as it's
been stated so far
says we want to be fully
invested across our m assets.
And what are the
optimal portfolios?
Well, what if we want to invest
some of our money, our capital,
just in cash?
Or not invest our full
capital and invest
the rest in the portfolio?
So if we consider adding
a risk-free asset,
then this is an asset.
We'll call it the 0th asset.
It has, say, some
expected return or not.
It's risk free.
So that's a constant.
It has zero variance.
And if we're investing as well
in that possible risky asset,
then we can basically
consider investing w weights
in the risky asset
and 1 minus w times
the unit vector in
the risk-free asset.
And let's see, I want
to draw this graph here.
Let's see.
OK, suppose we have
two assets where
this is the efficient set.
And we consider now allowing
for a risk-free asset
to be invested in as well.
Well, that risk-free asset
is basically this point here.
And it has mean
r_0 and variance 0.
Now, if we combine this asset
with any of these portfolios,
what's the feasible
set going to be?
Well, we can basically
invest some money
in the risk-free asset
and some in asset 2.
So we can get any
point along this line.
Basically, if we invest
in the risk-free asset--
if we invest some
fraction in asset 2
and the remainder in
the risk-free asset,
then our expected return
is the linear line
between r_0 and alpha_2.
And the volatility of
a weighted average--
of a fraction of asset
2 has a volatility
given by whatever that weight
is times the volatility.
So this point here corresponds
to, say, w times sigma_2
for its volatility and r_0
plus w times alpha_2 minus r_0.
Now the dramatic thing
is that we actually
are able to achieve an
improvement over points
on the efficient frontier, such
as, say, the minimum variance
portfolio.
And if we consider
the fraction here,
we have a higher return
and a lower variance
than the minimum
variance portfolio
that we considered before.
And so investing in
the risk-free asset
does sort of enlarge
our opportunity
space quite dramatically.
And there are some very special
results that come from this.
So let's go through
the mathematics
for solving this problem.
And in the lecture
notes, I'm going
to go over this pretty
quickly-- really,
when you go through
it slowly you'll say,
oh, this is very
straightforward and logical.
So we're basically going to
minimize the volatility subject
to the constraint that the
return is equal to alpha_0.
We define the Lagrangian and
do the first-order conditions,
solve those.
And if we solve those, we
get-- basically lambda_1
has this nice form here.
And this is obtained by
just very simple equation
solving of those two
first-order conditions.
And if we have m
assets available
when we look at the
solution, then we
get an optimal
portfolio that has
a w_0 vector given by this
solution and a lambda_1
given by this solution.
Now w_0 is the proportion
or is the allocation
to the risky assets.
What varies depending on our
target return alpha_naught,
is simply this lambda_1
Lagrangian multiplier.
Basically, alpha_0,
our target return,
only affects the
value of lambda_1.
And our weights
across the risky asset
is a simple multiple of a fixed
vector of relative weights.
And this fixed vector
of relative weights
is the inverse of a covariance
matrix across the assets
times alpha minus 1_m R_0.
And so what we
have is a portfolio
that basically invests in the
risky assets in the same way.
The only thing that
differs is how much weight
we give to that
particular portfolio.
As we increase lambda_1,
then we give more allocation
to this fixed vector of weight.
So we invest proportionally
in the assets.
And we just scale how
much that overall factor
is to achieve different
levels of return.
OK, we can get nice, closed-form
expressions for the portfolio
variance just as an extension
of the two-asset case.
Basically the portfolio
variance is a parabola
in the target return.
And so as we increase
our target return,
we have to increase our
portfolio variability.
There is that trade-off when
we use optimal portfolios.
And if we consider the fully
invested optimal portfolio,
well, the fully invested
portfolio-- and that's
nothing in cash,
invest everything
in the risky
assets-- we actually
are going to call that
the market portfolio.
And the expressions
here give us the weights
for that market portfolio.
And this may look a
little complicated
in terms of the expressions.
But it's actually quite
simple closed-form expressions
for the expected
return and the variance
of the market portfolio.
And what's happening with
this is we have-- basically,
for the risky assets we
have some efficient or set
of feasible portfolios,
which is all in this range.
And then with our risky asset,
we could be investing here.
And so the optimal
portfolio, in the case
where we can invest in
the risk-free asset,
will basically
correspond to sort
of maximizing the mean
return across all portfolios.
So it's actually
going to correspond
to the simple tangent line,
which basically crosses
the market portfolio, which is
the fully invested portfolio.
Now, this structure
of the problem
is actually incredibly powerful.
And there's an important
paper by Tobin,
which states that basically
every portfolio is going
to-- under these assumptions
for the investment problem--
every optimal portfolio
invests in a combination
of the risk-free asset
and the market portfolio.
So regardless how much
risk you want to take,
the optimal portfolio
is essentially the same.
It just depends on
how much capital
you're going to put into
that optimal portfolio.
And so all of the
optimal portfolios
will invest in the
same risky assets
as the market portfolio
in same proportions.
And the only difference
is their total weight.
Now, plugging in the expressions
for the different Lagrange
multipliers for a given
portfolio, P, with return--
and we get that expression.
So let me just summarize that.
So suppose we want
the portfolio P such
that the expectation of
our P is equal to alpha_0,
then this portfolio R_P is
going to equal-- basically, it's
going to invest in the
risk-free asset with 1
minus 1 transpose w_m
plus w_m transpose--
I'm sorry, w_m times the
return of the market.
And the actual weights are
given by this expression
here, which gives us the
expression that I was just
writing up on the board.
We have the expected return
is r_0 plus w_m times market
return minus r_0.
And the volatility,
sigma squared P,
is simply the square of
the weight in the market
times the market volatility.
This leads to the definition
of basically the capital market
line, which is essentially
this line here.
This is our capital market line
for the portfolio optimization.
And the structure
of this line is such
that this point for the
market portfolio that
has volatility given by the
market portfolio's volatility
sigma_m and the return
on the market alpha_m,
or expected value of R_m.
And the slope of this line
is given by alpha_m minus r_0
over sigma_m.
And points along the line
are given by r_0 plus sigma_p
times this factor.
So this is the
expected value of R_p
is any optimal
portfolio has return
equal to the risk-free
rate plus a multiple
of the return per risk
of the market portfolio.
This term here is called
the price of market risk.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Is that the
same as the Sharpe ratio?
PETER KEMPTHORNE: It's
close to the Sharpe ratio.
The Sharpe ratio is--
yes, this is the Sharpe
ratio for the market portfolio.
And so, if we want to
invest in the market,
our decision is
reduced to how much
risk are we willing to take.
And the compensation for taking
extra risk is extra return.
And we achieve that by
essentially investing
in the same portfolio, only we
change the scale at which we're
investing in that portfolio.
So far we've been
considering sort
of points between being
fully invested in the market
or fully invested in cash.
If we are able to borrow
money at the risk-free rate,
then we can basically
allocate additional weights
to the market
portfolio and achieve
points that are beyond--
have higher return,
higher volatility than
the market portfolio.
We can basically
lever the strategy
by borrowing money and investing
that in this market portfolio.
So the efficient frontier,
if we can borrow risklessly,
would just be the capital
market line extended.
Here's a listing
of the papers that
go through sort of the
classical foundations for this.
These are all
accessible on the web.
And I encourage you to
actually look at these papers,
because the arguments
are very straightforward.
The motivation and background
is interesting to read.
Virtually everyone on this page
actually has a Nobel Prize,
except Lintner, I think he
died before they gave the Nobel
Prize to Markowitz and
Sharpe, but he certainly
would've been
included in this case.
AUDIENCE: And the latest one.
PETER KEMPTHORNE: Pardon me?
AUDIENCE: The latest.
PETER KEMPTHORNE: And the
latest one, yes, yes, Fama
was just awarded,
what, two weeks ago.
All right, let's move on to
von Neumann-Morgenstern Utility
Theory.
Now, in the Markowitz
mean-variance analysis
we sort of reduced
all portfolios
to the properties of what's
their expected return
and what's their variance or
volatility of the returns.
Under what circumstances would
that be a really good decision
to be making for how to
do portfolio optimization,
portfolio allocations?
Well, the von
Neumann-Morgenstern theory
is a theory which
motivates making decisions
under uncertainty, where
you should specify a utility
function for your
wealth, and you
should engage in decisions
that maximize the expected
utility of your wealth.
And the theory is
really very powerful
in that when you're making
decisions under uncertainty,
there are sort of rational
things you should do.
If you like higher
return, the decision
should be consistent
with preferring outcomes
with higher returns.
If you don't like
variability, then you
should be preferring
returns that
have the same expected return,
that have lower volatility.
But depending on how your
utility function is defined,
you may get different outcomes.
And so to set up this problem,
let's just consider the problem
that Markowitz addressed.
You have a one-period
investment.
You start with
initial wealth W_0.
You're going to
choose a portfolio P.
And the wealth
after one period is
simply going to be 1 plus
the return on that portfolio,
giving terminal wealth W.
And our utility function
is going to be some quantitative
measure of the outcome, what's
the value to the investor.
And we'd simply want to
compute the expected volatility
of different strategies
and find the strategy that
maximizes the expected utility.
What are the basic properties
of utility functions?
Well, if we graph over
wealth, our utility of wealth,
starting at W_0,
our initial wealth,
if we have greater
wealth, presumably we'll
have greater utility.
So the slope of the utility
function should be increasing.
Perhaps as we get
more and more wealthy,
the marginal benefit
of additional wealth
isn't quite as much as
it was when we were poor.
And so perhaps the curve
for the utility function
should taper off a bit.
OK, these conditions
would correspond
to the first derivative
being increasing always
and the second derivative
being less than 0 perhaps.
There are definitions
in the literature
of risk aversion, absolute risk
aversion, and relative risk
aversion.
And these are
simple functions of
the first and second derivatives
of the utility function.
To see where these
come into play,
let's assume the utility
function is a smooth function
and consider a Taylor series
approximation of that.
So if we consider expanding
the utility function
about some base wealth
W star, then it's
simply equal to
that value of W star
plus first derivative
times W minus W star
plus 1/2 the second derivative
times the squared deviation
of the wealth from W star.
And if we take
expectations of this,
and if W star is
the actual expected
wealth of the random variable,
then this expected utility
is actually proportional
to the expected
wealth minus 1/2 lambda times
the variance of the wealth.
So sort of to a second order
of approximation, this expected
utility is a function
which is looking
at expected return minus a
multiple of the volatility
of that return, or
the wealth if we're
considering it on that scale.
So there are various
different utility functions
that economists
have worked with.
And basically the kinds of
functions they work with
are all the simple functions
we as mathematicians
know about, linear functions,
quadratic functions,
exponential functions, power
functions, and log functions.
So these are just the
first ones to come
to mind for economists perhaps.
But there's actually
some rich theory
in terms of sort of investment
choice with different utility
functions of these types.
And there is some interesting
work there in the economics
literature.
One thing that is
to be pointed out
is that with quadratic
utility, then
if we consider the
expected utility
under quadratic utility,
that is the expected utility
function that only
depends on expected
wealth and the variance of
the wealth, which depends only
on the expected return and
the variance of the return
of the portfolio.
So if we are working with a
quadratic utility function,
then this mean-variance
analysis is the right thing
to be doing under the
von Neumann-Morgenstern
expected utility theory.
So doing that is a good
decision under that
if that's the utility function.
Now when is that solution
not to be preferred?
Well, really it's
not be preferred
if you have a different
utility function possibly.
And maybe the utility
function should
be adding some penalties
for skewness or kurtosis.
And that's being ignored here.
So extensions can be looked at.
An interesting mathematical fact
is that under the assumption,
or should I say the
imagination, that returns
are Gaussian distributed, then
the sort of means and variances
of portfolios
completely characterize
all the distributions
of portfolios of assets,
if the underlying assets
are Gaussian distributions.
So a mean-variance
analysis is actually
optimal under non-quadratic
utility functions,
if the underlying assets
are Gaussian distributions,
because only the means
and variances are
going to characterize
the optimal portfolios
and properties of those.
And I guess, the
stochastic dominance
of functions of these
variables will generally
apply when there's that
corresponding stochastic
dominance in terms of
their means and variances.
Anyway, this kind of
theory can get involved.
It allows us to extend the basic
model that we consider here.
Let's turn then to the topic
of the portfolio constraints.
So far, in looking
at this problem,
we haven't made any
constraints on the problem.
We just want to maximize return,
minimize variance, and consider
trade-offs between those.
With practical portfolio
optimization problems,
there are different constraints
that come into play.
Portfolios that are long
only constrain the weights
to only be positive.
There can be
holding constraints,
which it may be that we don't
want the amount of a given
asset to be too big.
There's the equity
strategies, you
don't want to be
holding-- if you
have a sort of medium-frequency
trading strategy in equities,
you don't want to be holding
much more than the trading
volume of a few hours or
maybe a day in the asset,
because if you happen
to have to sell it,
there really won't be
liquidity to trade that.
But we can add--
There's a simple linear
constraints on the holdings.
There could be
turnover constraints.
If we're considering basically
adjusting our portfolio
from one period
to the next, there
are limits in terms of
how much we can actually
trade of the different assets.
There can be benchmark
exposure constraints.
Suppose we want to invest
in a portfolio that's
very much like there's a
market index, say, the S&P 500.
But we want to try and do
better than the S&P 500.
But we want to protect ourselves
from basically not being
very close to the benchmark
if our bets, basically,
an allocation, are wrong.
Then one basically can
control how different
from the benchmark
allocation we are limit,
then limit that departure
so we can basically
limit how far from the benchmark
weights we want our portfolio
to be.
And this is useful basically
for considering strategies
that do as well or better than
particular benchmark indices.
Related to this is our
tracking error constraints.
In addition to basically not
having allocation weights that
depart much from the
benchmark weights,
we can consider how
much variation is there
in our portfolio compared
with an underlying benchmark.
And we can consider tracking
error between our portfolio
P and the underlying benchmark
and measure that tracking error
in terms of variability,
that difference,
and want to control that.
There are also risk
factor constraints.
In equity markets there
are many different factors
that affect returns.
And these factors can be
identified empirically
and controlled for by
limiting the exposure
to different factors
in the portfolio.
We'll see this in next lecture.
But basically if there
are underlying factors
f, which-- basically a
return on the asset i
can be explained by sort of an
idiosyncratic alpha for that
asset, plus certain
correlations with market factors
f, and then a residual
innovation epsilon.
And so the returns on these
assets can be explained perhaps
50% by underlying market forces,
and given by the underlying
factors f_(j, t), which
are constant across i.
So these are affecting all
the stocks with different
coefficients beta_(i,k).
And in our portfolio,
we may want
to limit the exposure
to a given factor.
And with many
strategies, you actually
want to neutralize the portfolio
to those market risk factors.
So we can actually
constrain our weights
to have zero exposure across
these different market factors.
There are other constraints,
minimum transaction size--
generally it's the case
that trades in equities
are in 100 share units,
although that's changing.
There can be minimum
holding sizes.
And there's also
integer constraints
that can be applied.
If you're trading assets that
have sort of large values,
then these integer constraints
actually come into play.
If you're trading Google
stock, and how much
is Google stock worth now?
AUDIENCE: $800.
PETER KEMPTHORNE:
Something like that.
So compare that with Ford, which
is like $50, or I don't know,
but there's orders of
magnitude difference.
So integer constraints
can come into play.
If you're dealing in
a very large size,
then these things don't
really have much impact.
But they can with
smaller portfolios.
Now, all of these
different constraints
can be expressed as linear
and quadratic constraints
on the weights.
So the set-up for the
portfolio optimization problem
can be the same as
before, except we
add in these
additional constraints.
So we basically add in
additional Lagrange multipliers
times these
particular constraints
with their linear quadratic.
And we can implement the
portfolio optimization problem
that way.
Let me turn to an example.
Let's go-- OK, I want to
go through an example.
of-- OK, I want to consider US
sector exchange-traded funds
between 2009 and last week.
Basically, exchange-traded
funds allow
you to invest in equity markets
with sort of single assets
that represent
different sectors.
The ones that are
considered here
are basically
spider-traded funds,
which invest in the different
major industrial sectors
of the US market,
ranging from materials,
health care, consumer
staples, down
to technology and utilities.
Here is a graph of
the cumulative returns
of these nine different
exchange-traded funds
and over the period from
2009 up through last week.
And what one can
see is basically
they perform differently.
And what I'd like to do
is just examines what
would have been an
optimal allocation
across these exchange-traded
funds over this period.
So basically looking
back at the data
and seeing how our
portfolio analysis
tools would result in particular
application allocations.
So we can look at the
risk versus return
annualized of these.
Let's see-- this is-- I
guess that good enough.
Anyway, what you can see
is a volatility range
between 0 and 30.
Annualized want return
between 0 and 25.
We have the different
sectors in this plot.
So this is our
feasible set-- this
is the plot of return versus
volatility for these nine
exchange-traded funds.
This happens to be utilities.
There's financials over there.
Here's consumer staples.
Very top is a consumer
discretionary.
Let's see, I applied a
mean-variance optimization
to this problem,
assuming that there's
a constraint of 30% of
the capital per asset.
So we don't want to
invest more than 30%
of the capital in any
single exchange-traded fund.
And this graph here shows how,
as we vary our target return
from sort of the
minimum value up
to the maximum value for
being fully invested,
how much of the capital
we're going to invest
in the different sectors.
So what you can see is
this yellow one, which
is consumer staples, is coming
in with a really high weight.
And the green is
energy-- let's see,
I think it's energy--
that is the next one.
And orange is health.
And what's important
to see is that when
we're looking at sort of the
lower range of the returns,
basically expecting returns
above the risk-free rate that's
very low, then the
relative proportion
investment in the different
assets is the same.
Basically, these allocations
are slowly scaling up,
just linearly.
And that corresponds
to investing
in the optimal portfolio without
constraints with a fixed value.
But once we hit the 30%
then that constraint
starts to be active.
And we can't invest
anymore in that.
So we have to add more
to other securities.
And so basically more is given
to the consumers discretionary
and the other.
Now actually here's another
graph of the same data,
just stacking the allocation.
So we consider ranging from how
are we investing our capital.
This dark red is how much
money we invest in cash.
And then these
colored lines indicate
by their vertical
length how much
we're investing in the
different exchange traded funds.
So basically as
the constraints get
hit, the portfolio
sort of change
in terms of their
overall structure.
And what can happen
is-- actually
as we're trying to achieve
more and more return,
well, there may
not be assets that
provide that additional
return, or there
may be a very few assets
that provide that return.
And so in this case,
technology stocks
are coming in as
we're trying to get
really high levels of return
in our optimal portfolios.
And so if we really
want that higher return,
that's going to
come at higher risk.
And we actually
are de-allocating
some from the consumer staples
and consumer discretionary
at that point.
OK, here's a graph of the
efficient frontier as estimated
with the data.
And what you can see is
that these portfolios,
optimal portfolios,
yield improvements
over each of the individual
exchange-traded funds,
in terms of having higher
return with lower risk.
And if we consider just a
target return of 10%-- OK,
there's the portfolio.
I've graphed here
sort of in solid blue
what the optimal portfolio
with a 10% volatility.
That's the solid
blue line there.
So these are the results with
this 30% capital constraint.
Now how is this
problem going to change
if we reduce the capital
constraint from 30% per asset
to 15%?
Who can comment on
what will change?
AUDIENCE: I'm a little confused.
Could you put a constraint
on the risk-free asset.
Could you do that as well?
PETER KEMPTHORNE: Well, the
risk-free asset has no risk.
And so putting a
constraint-- well,
you could put a constraint
on it in terms of it
not going negative and it
not being greater than one.
So in fact that is a constraint.
Those are constraints
being imposed here.
But, I guess, in some-- well,
there are, like I guess,
endowments, say, that have
investment policies that
say that they want a certain
fraction assets invested
in risky assets and not in cash.
So that is a
realistic constraint
in certain circumstances.
And this is just highlighting
how the allocations vary
across the risky
asset if we only
have very simple constraints
on the cash investment.
Well, the question
I want to focus on
is what happens if we make
the maximum allocation
constraint more severe.
So it's 15% instead of 30%.
Then what's going to happen is
these capital constraints are
going to start hitting sooner.
So we have to allocate to the
other exchange traded funds.
So let me show you how that
works out with the same graph.
Let's see-- OK, let me just
close that and then we go here.
OK, this shows with
a 15% allocation,
how the allocations vary.
And I'll be posting this
on the course website.
But it turns out the efficient
frontier is actually lower.
Basically, for higher
returns, we actually
can't get those higher
returns by getting
the biggest bang for the buck.
We don't want to allocate
too much to those higher
return, higher risk securities.
And so the optimal, the
efficient frontier as estimated
basically slopes down.
Now, with this
particular example
of these exchange-traded
funds and how
you allocate across those,
this provides some insight
into portfolio optimization.
It's not really a
realistic setting,
because we're
looking over the past
and using the actual
sample performance
to define these portfolios.
Let me just highlight an
example of applying these kinds
of methods with a-- is it here?
Yep, OK.
Is that the right graph?
OK, suppose we
consider not investing
in exchange-traded funds.
But we are a hedge fund.
And we have sector
pricing models
across all these
different sectors.
And what we can do is
consider going long/short
in these sectors.
And in fact, we consider sort
of a market-neutral strategy,
sector by sector, and
consider investing sector
by sector in these different
sector-based models.
OK, here's a graph of
different multi-factor pricing
models for trading
market-neutral programs
within each of the nine
industrial sectors,
the same ones corresponding
to the exchange-traded funds.
And because these strategies
are market-neutral,
the sort of total
returns over-- this
is a five-year period--
are rather modest, namely
sort of 60% for some of the
models, 20% for other models
What's particularly
relevant with these models
though is that they tend
to be less correlated.
And the diversification
benefits can be rather dramatic.
And so here is a graph of
the optimal allocations
across these different
sector market-neutral models.
And we can see
that this red model
is getting a lot of weight.
That actually is
the utility sector.
And then these other models
are industrials and energy.
And so if we consider
investing in these,
we can actually achieve a
target volatility of 10%--
we're going to achieve
this solid blue line--
as the portfolio strategy.
And one can see how by combining
these assets together--
these assets are different
market-neutral trading
models-- we have to get
quite a bit of benefit
from the portfolio optimization.
And the greater benefit in
the portfolio optimization
is because these strategies tend
to have much lower correlations
with each other.
Let's go back now, finish up
with-- how do we go back here?
Where's my red dot?
OK, just to finish up the
discussion, with these methods
it's important to highlight
that what we've been using
were estimated returns,
estimated volatilities,
and correlations.
And these estimates can have
a huge impact on the results.
There's basically choices
of estimation period.
There's estimation error.
Different techniques can
modulate these issues.
Exponential moving
average are often applied.
Having dynamic factor
models is used.
Basically, rather than
using sample estimates
of the variance/covariance
matrix,
using factor models to estimate
the variance-covariance matrix
results in more precise
inputs to the optimization.
And finally, just with
different risk measures--
we've been focusing on
portfolio volatility
and minimizing that-- the
methodologies can be extended
to have different
measures of risk--
mean absolute deviation, for
example, or semi-variance.
In terms of the motivation
for squared volatility
and minimizing that, you'll
recall that in likelihood
analysis of Gaussian
distributions,
the sort of squared
deviations from the means
are characterizing variability.
Well, if we focus on mean
absolute deviation, then
probability distributions
where the distributions relate
to the absolute deviation
from the mean characterizing
the distribution
might be appropriate.
And indeed, distributions
with heavier tails,
like exponential
distributions, are
appropriate when we consider
mean absolute deviation.
So some alternate
risk measures are
appropriate when the
volatility measure
itself isn't necessarily
appropriate because
of the distributional
assumptions.
Semi-variance was introduced
actually by Markowitz,
where you're interested in
controlling the downside risk
as opposed to the upside risk.
There's value-at-risk
measures which
are now completely standard
in portfolio management
and management of risky assets,
where one is actually-- well,
this is introduced
by Ken Abbott in one
of the first few lectures.
Value at risk is
a very simple idea
of characterizing
what outcome is
sort of the threshold
of extreme, at say
the 5% level or the 1%
level, and to basically keep
and monitor the value at risk.
So if we had a risk
that was basically
in the worst 5%
or 1% of the time.
What is that level?
That's the value at risk.
That as a nice risk measure is
simple to define and reasonably
simple to estimate.
But it doesn't characterize sort
of what the potential exposure
is if you exceed that.
And there are
extensions of that.
The conditional
value at risk which
is looking at the
expected loss given
that you exceed the
value at risk threshold.
And this method is
now-- I think it's
been going to be incorporated
into regulatory requirements
for banks in terms of
how they measure risk.
Right now, I believe it's
almost all value at risk.
Extensions like this
conditional value at risk
is definitely going
to be applied.
And in the discussion of
different risk measures,
there's literature
talking about what
are appropriate risk measures
and how do we define those.
Well, it really depends
on what your assets are
and if your assets are simply
simple investments in stocks
or bonds, sort of cash
assets or cash instruments,
then value at risk
is quite reasonable.
If you're investing
in derivatives,
which have non-linear payoffs,
then things get complicated.
And so things need to be handled
on a case by case basis there.
But if you're interested
in risk analysis,
there's a whole discussion
on coherent risk measures
that you can look into.
That's quite interesting.
OK, let's stop there.
Thank you.